you're anything like me you can't walk
past a mirror without checking yourself
out alone this world is in no shortage
of people who are fascinated with making
muscles and making them a little bit
bigger so in this episode of 5-minute
physiology I'm gonna take you behind the
scenes and show you what exactly it
looks like from the perspective of the
muscle cell when you hypertrophy so
let's jump in and take a look at it well
we first have to understand that all of
your muscles are comprised of thousands
if not millions of small individual
little muscle fibers you don't have to
know all the terminology on the screen
there but to get the basic sense this is
what it would look like right so what
you're seeing here is a muscle sample
that I took from a professional athlete
it's actually happens to be a world
champion in the picture on the right
hand side you can see them kind of
lining it up but then I'm zoomed it in
there
that's what actual muscle tissue looks
like so if I take it directly out of you
put it on a petri dish and kind of line
it up vertically each one of those
little lines or bundles is what we call
in I have several hundred individual
muscle cells within it so if we go back
to our original picture we can see that
imagine this image I'm showing you is
your bite and one of your bicep muscles
the entire muscle itself is made up of
all these individual muscle cells well
in order for that bicep to then get
bigger one of two things has to happen
number one you could increase the
diameter or the size of any of those
individual cells that's what we call
muscle hypertrophy ok so that was again
an increase in diameter of any
individual muscle cell the only other
thing that could make the bicep as a
whole bigger would be hyperplasia now
we'll talk about this in a separate
video I have some very controversial
views on that but that would be the
addition of individual muscle fibers
themselves ok so most people are gonna
tell you hyperplasia doesn't happen and
it probably doesn't under normal
circumstances that much again maybe if
you're nice to me I'll make a separate
video video explain to you my views on
hyperplasia but for now let's disregard
it okay so for the most part making your
bicep bigger means that you have made
all of those are most of those
individual muscle cells themselves a
little bit thicker so this is an actual
image of what it would look like so on
the top there that running horizontally
is a three-dimensional image it was a
three-dimensional image that I made into
a two-dimensional image of an individual
muscle fiber so we use some pretty fancy
technology and some microscopes and what
you're seeing there in the red are those
these contractile fibers on myosin and
actin we'll talk about a second and the
blue or the nuclei all right but the
point is that's one individual muscle
cell in fact if you've had anatomy or
physiology you can see those vertical
lines running up and down and those
aren't bad quality pictures those are
the actual sarcomeres so those are the Z
lines that makes sense.you what would
happen if you were to go through muscle
hypertrophy is that individual fiber
would then again increase its diameter
and that's what it would look like so
you can see again the nuclei really
clear there dr. Jimmy Bagley my
colleague has a tremendous amount of
these photos this is what he does so
check him out on social media and
everything else if you like to see
videos of muscle like this what actually
gets bigger okay we know the fiber gets
larger but why does the fiber itself get
larger well we have to take a quick look
at the micro anatomy of a muscle cell so
when you huge fi a muscle fiber our
muscle cell these are interchangeable
terms here's what basically has to
happen imagine the green circle there is
one of those individual muscle fibers
and instead of running at long ways like
this I've just stacked it and we look
straight down at it right so look at the
circle well for muscle to contract we
have two primary filaments that were
interested in one of them's called actin
it is called myosin now for every
individual myosin there are six actin
that's surrounded and effectively what
happens when muscles contract is the
mice and reach up grab the actin pull
them together that shortens the length
of the muscle those microfilaments are
myofilaments stack on top of each other
and the muscle gets larger all right you
can google sliding filament theory if
you've never heard of this and learn
more but for the purpose of this video
that's what's going to look like so
again we're still talking one individual
muscle cell well what happens when you
hypertrophy is this
so what those little pinkish fuchsia
something
colory things myosin actually look like
is they've got a big globular head on
one end and they kind of are in
intertwine back and forth and we'd like
to teach this and basic anatomy but
that's not really what it actually looks
like it probably more realistically
looks like that and so those little
purple heads again will go up grab and
act in they'll kind of over pull
the actin towards it and you got our
contraction and those are actually
running three-dimensional space so there
are all parts of the myosin filament and
so again we have those if I'm looking
directly at you there's a macton actin
act and act and act and act enter
whatever six was and then we have these
little myosin heads that are kind of
wrapped all around and they can reach up
and grab these actin at any point of
space well when you've committed too
much life atrophy what the body does is
that and so it doesn't add more total
myosin it takes the current amount of
myosin you have typically and increases
the amount of protein and so the term we
would say here is we increase myosin
protein we didn't increase the total
number of myosin filaments you can't add
myosin filaments but you have to add
equal proportions of actin because if
you just start adding myosin instead of
having six actin around every myosin you
now have two minus n around every three
actin or there'd be one to one and and
it wouldn't be a good ratio and that
throws off our contractile function of
our muscle now other animals do have
different combinations six to one is
pretty unique to human but that's really
what happens so for the most part we're
adding myosin protein that's the point
the major take-home I wanted to get
across in this video is the filament
number typically stays the same when we
get it there so to give you that visual
again this is what it would look like
you're taking those individual ones I'm
just representing the fact that there
are six myosin here if you want and oh
look at that the diameter of the myosin
filaments themself gets thicker because
we added more myosin protein same thing
happens acting probably by the way we
don't know fully exactly this process so
maybe I'll come back in a year or ten or
five years and say oh this parts wrong
this part was right it's not exactly
perfectly known but this is as best as
we understand it now joining us back the
video because the myosin filament got
thicker because we added more myosin
it kind of got started smashed up next
to each other and it's getting smashed
up too close it's called a lattice
spacing so the space between the actin
and the myosin gets too close I can't
really contract fully and so what you
have to do is take the entire cell and
start adding more links to the cell wall
so that the entire damnit or the cell
can get larger so that the spacing
between the myosin and actin can be
proper and so the first up again is you
would add more of these myosin these
acting you started getting bunched up
and now watch what happens here and now
as a result of that you have to increase
the diameter of the muscle cell and so
then the muscle cells start getting
smashed up next to each other and so
because that you start increasing the
space of the actual muscle itself right
so that's that's actually a hyper tree
of an individual muscle fiber that's why
your muscles get larger when you go
through size so coming back to our
original image here an increase in
diameter of a muscle fiber is typically
we refer to when we say muscle
hypertrophy and now you have a little
bit better understanding of what
constants that I hope you enjoyed the
video always check back for more I am
considering making a 25 or 55 minute
video of the muscle hypertrophy so let
me know in a comment below if you'd like
this and you'd like me to make that 55
one as always I do all these things for
free and actually I just realize I have
a patreon account but I have been
forgetting to charge people for the
videos so I uploaded a whole bunch of
things to patreon and didn't even charge
contributors so point being I really
make these videos to entertain and
inspire engage folks that don't have the
opportunity to go to school or or take
my class so if you're enjoying I would
appreciate some support just help share
it around get people to subscribe other
than that have it just a rock-solid day
one love one nation
[Music]
you